Looking to get started with
Microsoft Word? In this tutorial,
I am going to walk you through all of
the basics of Microsoft Word. Let's
check it out. If you do not have Microsoft
Word already installed on your computer,
you can download it for free at office.com
and create a free Microsoft 365 account.
Note that the free version is a lighter
version and you do need internet access
in order to use it. You can also purchase
the Microsoft 365 subscription plan online,
which allows you to download Word as well as
other Microsoft 365 products directly to your
computer. To get started once you have Word
on your computer, if you are using Windows,
click on the Start button and you can either
search for Microsoft Word in the toolbar or it
is likely already going to be pinned to your Start
screen. On a Mac, you can find Microsoft Word in
your Applications folder or by searching for it in
Spotlight. To get started, you have two options.
The first is to select New Blank Document. This
will give you a completely blank canvas from which
to begin. The other option is to start with a
template by clicking on New on the left-hand side.
Here you could browse or search for
various templates like flyers, letters,
and address labels. If you find a template that
you're interested in using, click on it and then
press Create. All of the templates that you
see here in Word are free for you to use. Now
let's get started by clicking on New Blank
Document. We'll start by touring the ribbon,
which is everything that could be found here above
the blank page. You'll probably spend most of your
time in Microsoft Word under the Home tab, in
large part because this is where you'll do all of
your text formatting. I'm going to paste something
that I previously wrote to show you some of the
different text options available to you. Here in
the Font section of your ribbon, you can bold,
italicize, and underline your text. You can also
change the font type altogether. And you could do
this either at the beginning of writing your blank
document or if you've already written something,
you can highlight the text and then adjust the
font. Next to the font type is the font size. Some
of the other options are to add text effects, use
the highlighter to mark up your page, or adjust
the font color. An often overlooked feature on
Microsoft Word is the strike through option.
This could be helpful if you're making lists and
checking them off. My favorite text formatting
tool is the paintbrush. Let's say I want to
adjust my text formatting here. So I'm going
to change my font type and let's go ahead and
bold it. If I like how this works and I want to
apply the same text formatting to other areas of
my document, it could be a rather manual process.
However, if you click on the paintbrush once,
you can then apply that same text formatting to
another area in your document. If you double click
on the paintbrush, it locks it, allowing you to
highlight other areas in your document and apply
the same text formatting. This could save you a
lot of time. You will have also noticed that when
I highlight text in my document, a pop-up toolbar
comes up, allowing you to use some of the most
commonly-accessed tools, which means less toggling
if you happen to be on something besides the home
tab. There's also keyboard shortcuts which could
be used for some of the most popular options.
For instance, ctrl plus B in order to bold
text. And while our tutorial today isn't going
to walk through all of the keyboard shortcuts,
if you hover over any one of these icons, Word
will provide you with the keyboard shortcut to
use. Now let's take a look at the paragraph
section. The most common reasons you would
come here to the paragraph area is to either add
bullet points to your page or adjust the alignment
of your text. Let's look at the alignment first.
Right now, all of my text is aligned to the left
of my page. If I wanted to align my text to
the right, I could do that here. Likewise,
I can align my text to be centered in the middle
of my document. If I want to add bullet points,
you can highlight the text that you want to be
in a bulleted list and then you have a handful of
options in which to choose from. You also have the
option to add a numerical bulleted list as well.
One of the other cool features under paragraph is
the multi-level list. This can be really helpful
especially in research projects or school projects
where you want to add additional information under
each one of your bulleted items. If you're ever
using Word and know what you want to do but have
forgotten where to locate the tool in which to
complete your task, you could click on search
and type it in which could be very helpful when
you're first learning how to use Word. Let's take
a look under the magnifying glass. I want to point
out one helpful feature which is find and replace.
If you want to locate a word or multiple words
in your document and replace them with something
else, let's say you spelled somebody's name
incorrectly or in this case if I want to change
all of the words in my document to Microsoft
Word. You could do that here and either replace
some, all, or just locate those words in your
document. In this case, Word has gone ahead and
made four replacements on my behalf. Next is
another one of my favorite tools which is the
dictate button. Once you click on this microphone,
Microsoft Word will write down everything that
you say, allowing you to save time by just
speaking to your computer instead of typing.
I've actually created a separate video that
you can watch here in order to see all of the
different features of the dictate tool, including
transcription. Let's move on now to the insert tab
which is located next to the home tab. This is
where you come if you want to insert something
onto your page. The first one being a table. You
would drag and drop your mouse to select the table
size that you need created. You'll notice that
once you've created a table, two new tabs will
open up here at the top, table design and table
layout. I created a table earlier that I'm going
to paste into my document to show you some of the
editing features available. The first being adding
shading to your document. This is different than
adjusting the font color because you're actually
changing the color of the cells itself within
the table. If you want to adjust the text, you
can highlight the text that you want adjusted and
your pop-up toolbar of font options will appear
for you. Another feature is changing the borders.
This can either mean changing the border style
such as the color or the type of line used as well
as the weight or changing the border or removing
it entirely. In this case, I'm going to select no
border. This means that my text will still stay
aligned and organized in my document, but it won't
look like a traditional table. Here under table
layout, you can add additional cells or remove
them from your table without having to create
a new one. If I need to add a project number six,
instead of creating a new table, I can click into
this column and click on insert to the right
and this will create a new column for me. Let's
say I want to remove the entire row of completion
information. I can select that and then come here
to delete and delete the entire row without having
to recreate my entire table. Let's exit tables and
see some of the other things that we can insert
into our Word document. To add a photo or image
to your Word document, select the pictures icon.
You can pull an image from your device or from
a curated library of images that Microsoft
Word has available for free. In this example,
I'm going to drag an image from my computer and of
course you can always copy and paste as well. This
will open up a new picture format tab at the top
of my screen where you can make various artistic
edits to your picture. One of the most helpful
edits that you can make is to the layout options
or format of the picture. If I were to drag this
image now and try to move it around my page,
the text is going to realign. If I want the text
to follow the image, I can click on this and then
select tight text wrapping. This allows my image
to fit in more seamlessly with the document and I
find it particularly helpful when you're creating
flyers or presentations. In addition to adding
images, this is also where you would come if
you want to insert shapes or lines onto your
page as well as icons. And if you can't locate
the icon that you're looking for, you can always
utilize the search toolbar. This is also where
you would find the insert chart feature. You'll
have different options available to you on the
left-hand side and then you can further customize
them using the variations above. Once you open one
of these charts, Word will guide you as to how to
input the information needed in order to create
the best-looking chart. In addition to inserting
things like images, this is also where you would
come if you want to insert a header or a footer as
well as a page number into your document. Word
has various options that you can pick from in
terms of templates for your header and footer.
It's important to note that whatever you use as
your header or footer will appear on each page of
your document. Here I'll go ahead and add my text
and you can also insert images in your header and
footer as well. This might also be a good place
to include a date and time and you have different
available formats that you can choose from. Once
you're happy with how your header or footer looks,
you can either select close or simply click out of
that portion of their document. If you need
to make edits later on, simply double click
into your header or footer. Let's go ahead now and
add a footer onto our page. This is a good place
to include a page number which could be found
over here. You'll have different options as to
how you want the page number to appear and in this
case I'm going to select a bottom of the page and
align it in the middle. You can highlight this and
change the text and coloring as well. Now in some
cases you might not want the page number to appear
on the first page of your document. For instance,
if you have a table of contents or various
indexes. If that's the case, go back to page
number and select format page numbers. Here you
could choose what page you actually want it to
begin at. So, if I have a multi-page document
instead of the one appearing on page one,
it would actually appear on the second page of my
document which I want to be called page one. You
can also change the number format up here as well
depending on your needs. Let's now shift gears
and head over to the layout section. This is where
you can make changes to the margins or orientation
of your page. Here under margins, you'll see that
Microsoft defaults to normal margins. This is the
space that appears on the top left right and
bottom of each one of your pages. If you want
to change that, let's say make the margins more
narrow in order to fit more on your document, you
could select one of the presets. You can also make
custom margins here, which could be helpful if you
have particular guidelines that you need to follow
for a document or presentation. You can also make
changes to the orientation of your page, toggling
between portrait or landscape mode. This is also
where you would come if you wanted to add columns
to your page. For example, if I needed to create a
document with columns here, I could select this
and then I would have text on my left-hand side
but I could also click into the right hand side
and begin typing. One keyboard shortcut that I do
want to call out is ctrl plus z. This is the undo
button and can be very useful when making lots of
changes in your document, saving you lots of time.
Let's now move on to references. If you're putting
together a paper or presentation for school, this
tab can be a time saver. Let's start by looking at
how to add a table of contents. Before inserting
the table of contents into your document,
if you've already written something, you'll most
likely want to enter a new blank page into your
document. Go back to insert and select pages. You
can do this at any time and it's helpful if you
want to make changes in your document midstream.
Select blank page and it's automatically moved all
of your text down, leaving you with a blank page
to work from. You'll have a few options for the
table of contents. The first two options are
automatic tables and what that means is Word
will automatically look for headers within your
document and then automatically create a table of
contents using those headers, although you'll
likely always need to make small tweaks. The
other option is to insert a manual table. This is
where you'll go in manually and add the different
chapters or headers in your table of contents as
well as the corresponding page number. If you need
to add a citation to your document, Word makes it
really easy. Just put your cursor next to the area
you want to insert your citation and then click
add new source. First, you'll select the type
of source that you want to reference and
then follow the prompts to put in all of the
necessary information. Once you've entered this
information once, Word will automatically save it
so you don't have to recreate each citation
every time you need to reference it in your
document. Once you've put all of your citations
in, if you then choose to add a bibliography at
some point in your document, citations you've
already created will automatically appear,
making this super easy. Let's take a look at the
review tab. This is where you'll come to track
changes and make adjustments to your documents
such as spelling and grammar and other proofing.
You'll notice as you're writing your document
that sometimes words will be underlined in red.
This means that Word is suggesting that there's an
error that needs to be fixed, for instance if your
spelling is off. It's as simple as right clicking
and then making the adjustment based off of what
Word suggests and what makes the most sense for
you. You can also highlight a word and you'll get
some other options if you right click it. One
of those is synonyms which provides you with
suggestions for other words that you might want
to replace it with. Here under the proofing tab,
you can select word count and this will provide
you with statistics in terms of your word count,
paragraphs, lines, etc. for your entire document.
If you want to proofread your document by having
Microsoft read it aloud to you, place your mouse
before the first sentence that you want the words
to begin and then select read aloud. The most
common uses of Microsoft Word include writing
and editing documents, creating, etc. If you want
to change either the reading speed or the voice
selection, you can do that here under settings.
You can add comments to your document which can be
especially helpful if you're sharing and editing
this document with others for a school project or
a work assignment. Click on the document where you
want to enter the comment and select new comment.
You'll see that Word has automatically inserted
your name here based off of whatever Microsoft 365
account you're signed in as. You'll enter whatever
comment you have and then you can post it. Up here
on the top right-hand side you'll be able to see
all of the different comments in a document, so
if you're collaborating with others you'll be able
to see everything and either respond by replying,
giving it a thumbs up, or editing your own
comments. You can turn comments off and on
up here. If you're editing your document because
you're sharing this with others or perhaps you
want to track your own changes then you can
select tracking which will track all of the
changes either for yourself or that everyone
else is making in the document. For example,
if I want to change this word from readable to
accessible I then change the word and you'll see
that Microsoft Word has done a strike through for
the original word and added accessible underlined.
I can then hover over this and you'll be able to
see who and when that edit was made. If you're
editing this document for somebody else, you'll
then want to go up to changes and you can either
accept or reject the edits that were made that you
can view under tracking. You can either decide to
accept or reject all of the changes at once or one
at a time. Once you've accepted those changes the
red and underlined items will disappear. Now
that you've done all this great work in Word,
you're ready to save your document. Select file
and then save as. Here you'll be able to decide
where you want to save your document. Either you
can save it to the cloud if you have a OneDrive
attached to your account or directly onto your
PC or whatever device you're working on. Enter
a file name and then you can choose the format
that you want to save your document in. Most
of the time you'll be saving it in a Word
document which means that when you open it,
you'll reopen it within Microsoft Word. You can
also save your document as a PDF even if you don't
subscribe to Adobe. If you save it in PDF, you
can then either open it with PDF or send it to
others and they'll be able to open it in a PDF
file format. If you want to share your document
with others you have two options. The first is
to save your document and then attach it to an
email that you can send to whomever you want.
However, if you want to be able to collaborate
on a document and share tracking, comments, etc.
you'll need to share it via OneDrive. Click on
share and then you'll be prompted to upload it
to one of your various OneDrive or other cloud
accounts. Once you select the cloud account you
want to send it to, you'll rename your document.
Once you've uploaded the document to the cloud
you can choose whether those you share it with
can either edit the document or can view the
document but can't make any changes. You can
then enter their email addresses here. You can
include one person or multiple people and even
write them a personalized message before you send.
If you instead want to send this either by text
message or in your own email or even on a website
you can instead copy the link and share it. Again,
you have the option to either set it as a viewable
only document or an editable document. You can
even set an expiration date and a password for
making changes on any of your documents. Once
you're ready to send the link you can copy it and
it's available for you to copy and then paste and
send whomever you want to see your excellent work.
Now that you have these basic skills, you'll be
able to handle most tasks in Microsoft Word with
confidence. Let me know in the comments below
if you have any additional features you would
like to see a video about. Thanks for watching!